<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<dataset>
<templatetitle><span>Case Study: Human-Animal Relationships: Service Dogs</span></templatetitle>
<instruction>
    <instructionnorm><span>Scroll down to read each slide in the case study. When you have finished a slide, click on the arrow to go to the next slide. Read through the interaction as many times as you need. There is no time limit and this activity is not graded. </span></instructionnorm>
</instruction>
  <content>
    <leftcontent>
     <contenttitle>Human-Animal Relationships: Service Dogs—Introduction</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
      <para>Significant research has been done on the benefits of service dogs for the physical, emotional, and social well-being of patients with chronic illness or physical disability. However, little is known about their impact on immediate family members who live with the patients. This study explores the impact of service dogs on the physical, social, and emotional well-being of patients’ families. A better understanding of this topic would enable occupational therapists and other health care professionals to better advise and support their clients.</para>
       
      </contentdata>
     </leftcontent>
     <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="A young woman in a wheelchair petting a large Siberian Husky dog with one blue eye and one yellow eye. A young woman is standing next to the woman in the wheelchair holding the dog on a leash." picname="30732054618_074bc3d7dc_o.jpg"></picture>
        <imagecitation>"Sasha-Cisco reunion adoption" by Shutters Shelters/flickr, CC BY 2.0</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>
  
  <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Human-Animal Relationships: Service Dogs—The Study</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
        <para>While limited research currently exists on the effects of service dogs on patients' family members, and the studies that have been done have focused on parents of child patients rather than spouses or romantic partners of adult patients, previous research has indicated that adult patients who received service dogs reported needing less informal assistance from friends or family members than before. Based on this, researchers Jessica Bibbo, Kerri E. Rodriguez, and Marguerite E. O'Haire (2019) concluded that "fewer hours spent actively caregiving may not only decrease the partner’s or spouse's stress but may also improve their interpersonal relationship with the [service dog] recipient" (under "Psychosocial Effects of Service Dogs").</para>
       
        </contentdata>
      </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture  alt="A service dog lying on the floor in the foreground while a male patient undergoes physical therapy in the background" picname="2015_Army_Trials_150323-A-XY211-003.jpg"></picture>
        <imagecitation>"Army Trials 150323" by Sgt. 1st Class Christophe Paul/U.S. federal government, Public Domain</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>
  

  <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Human-Animal Relationships: Service Dogs—The Study</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
        <para>Bibbo, Rodriguez, and O’Haire hypothesized that the presence of a service dog in a patient’ home would be associated with both improvements in psychosocial health of family members in the home and a reduction in negative impacts of the patient's chronic condition. They evaluated this hypothesis along three main indicators: family members’ psychosocial health, health-related quality of life (HRQOL), and family functioning. The researchers also examined family members' relationships with the service dog and how those relationships affected outcomes.</para>
         
      </contentdata>
    </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="A woman sitting in her wheelchair holding the leash of her black lab service dog, greets a young service dog in training wearing a vest. He is held by his trainer. Three people are standing in the background observing the encounter." picname='8268103888_b545f47f75_o.jpg'></picture>
        <imagecitation>"Guide Dogs Greet at the NRC Sponsored CFC Charity Fair" by Nuclear Regulatory Commission/flickr, CC BY 2.0</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>

  

  <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Human-Animal Relationships: Service Dogs—Method</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
        <para>The researchers reached out to participants through Canine Assistants, a service dog placement provider for adults and children with chronic conditions or mobility issues. In all, the study involved 143 participants, but 17 were excluded from the final analysis, leaving an overall sample size of 126. Participants were organized into two groups: 50 family members of patients who were waiting for a service dog and 76 family members of patients who had already received one. The majority of participants were parents of child patients; only eight in the waitlist group and four in the received group were partners of adult patients.</para>
         <para>The participants were recruited via emails followed by phone calls. All participants provided informed consent. The family members’ participation consisted of completing a one-time survey. The researchers obtained demographic information and medical history from the patients’ initial applications for a service dog.</para>
      </contentdata>
      </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="A young man sitting on an outdoor step and holding a young service dog in his lap" picname='Camp_Pendleton.jpg'></picture>
        <imagecitation>"Camp Pendleton Marine's Son Receives Service Dog" by Cpl. Keenan Zelazoski/U.S. federal government, Public Domain</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>

  <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Human-Animal Relationships: Service Dogs—Analysis</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
        <para>Upon completion of data collection, the researchers analyzed the data according to three main measures: the Pediatric Quality of Life (PedsQL) Adult Quality of Life Inventory for "overall psychosocial health and domain-specific functioning," with components of emotional functioning, social functioning, and work/school functioning; the Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) for "patient-reported physical and psychosocial health," with short forms to measure anger, interpersonal companionship, and sleep quality (under "Psychosocial Health and Functioning"); and the PedsQL Family Impact Module, which assesses the impact of the patient’s condition in the domains of HRQOL, family functioning, communication, and worry. </para>
       
      </contentdata>
      </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="A young boy about 7 or 8 sitting on a rock outside reading to a tan dog sitting beside him. The dog has long hair around its face and perked up ears. There are bright colored flowers behind them." picname='17110495300_a023b7f23c_o.jpg'></picture>
        <imagecitation>"Library Story Hour Featuring American Red Cross Therapy Dogs" by USAG- Humphreys/flickr, CC BY 2.0</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>

  <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Human-Animal Relationships: Service Dogs—Results</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
        <para>Through respondent report and analysis, the researchers discovered that the presence of a service dog can have a statistically significant positive impact on family members in the home. While the presence of the service dog did not seem to directly affect overall psychosocial health or emotional or psychosocial functioning, researchers did find indirect positive effects related to the service dog’s work with the patient and a lessening of worry for the patient. In fact, the strongest association was with a decrease in worry about the patient’s health and future, though this association was strongest for parents of child patients; the evidence for partners of adult patients was not definitive due to the small number of partner participants. The presence of a service dog appeared to have no noticeable effect on family members’ anger, companionship, sleep, or functioning outside the home.</para>
       
      </contentdata>
      </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="A woman with two prosthetic legs is sitting in a chair and taking an object from the mouth of her service dog. The dog is a yellow lab." picname="2624411699_020b25d467_o.jpg"></picture>
        <imagecitation>"Service Dogs" by Elizabeth M. Lorge/The U.S. Army/flickr, CC BY 2.0</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>
  
 <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Human-Animal Relationships: Service Dogs—Discussion</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
        <para>One notable finding was a negative correlation between family members’ interactions with the service dog and their physical functioning in relation to the patient’s chronic condition. The researchers noted that according to previous research, parents, and mothers especially, “are often in charge of providing for the service dog’s daily needs,” which is “likely to compound the preexisting logistical requirements” of being a caretaker for a patient with a chronic condition (Bibbo, Rodriguez, and O’Haire 2019, under “Family Members’ Relationship with the Service Dog”). This information will be valuable for occupational therapists who are advising families about service dogs, especially families with young child patients (vs. adolescents or adults). Despite this drawback, the overall findings of the study showed significant evidence that service dogs can positively affect family members of patients as well as the patients themselves—primarily, though not solely, by alleviating worry for the patient.</para>
  

      </contentdata>
      </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="A service dog with a TV remote control in its mouth." picname='5011296794_a4d78ab83d_o.jpg'></picture>
        <imagecitation>"taro the shiba and a dynex tv remote 4" by Taro the Shiba Inu/flickr, CC BY 2.0</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>


  

  <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Human-Animal Relationships: Service Dogs—Future Study</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
     
       <para>Current literature has shown a strong positive correlation between the presence of a service dog and the health of the patient it is assigned to. Beyond the patient, family members living in the same house have also benefited from the presence of the service dog, but the extent of these benefits has been poorly researched. The researchers provide several suggestions for future study of the impacts on family members, including mediation analyses to better understand the relationships among outcome variables, an objective medical assessment of patients’ health at the time of the study, and a more complete assessment of family members’ psychosocial health. They also recommend that future studies use sample groups of a single type of family member—such as parents, spouses, or siblings—and measure of "caregiving-specific constructs such as caregiver burden, satisfaction, and mastery" (Bibbo, Rodriguez, and O’Haire 2019, under "Limitations").</para>
        <para><h3>References/Content Citations, Attributions</h3></para>
          <para>Bibbo, Jessica, Kerri E. Rodriguez, and Marguerite E. O’Haire. 2019. "Impact of Service Dogs on Family Members’ Psychosocial Functioning." <em>American Journal of Occupational Therapy</em> 73 (3). <a target="_blank" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6533052/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6533052/</a>.</para>
      </contentdata>
   
      </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="Five service dogs of various breeds sitting in the grass and wearing their working vests. Two young girls sitting with the dogs and holding books." picname='17110467440_c241beec66_o.jpg'></picture>
        <imagecitation>"Library Story Hour Featuring American Red Cross Therapy Dogs" by USAG- Humphreys/flickr, CC BY 2.0</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>

</dataset>
