<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<dataset>
<templatetitle><span>Case Study: Cognitive Anthropology: Attraction and Misinformation</span></templatetitle>
<instruction>
    <instructionnorm><span>Scroll down to read each slide in the case study. When you have finished a slide, click on the arrow to go to the next slide. Read through the interaction as many times as you need. There is no time limit and this activity is not graded.</span></instructionnorm>
</instruction>
  <content>
    <leftcontent>
     <contenttitle>Cognitive Anthropology: Attraction and Misinformation—Introduction</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
      <para>Ours is a digitally social culture. The speed with which digital information travels and the number of people who are able to send and receive digital information are unprecedented. Intuitively, one might hope that this technology would be used for good. Unfortunately, this is not always the case, and our communication platforms can easily and efficiently be used to drive agendas. This study explores cognitive anthropology and cultural evolution as mechanisms for manipulating communication, information, and narratives.</para>
       
      </contentdata>
     </leftcontent>
     <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="A white piece of paper in a typewriter displaying the typed words “fake news”." picname="51120419628_5d1c85dcd2_o.jpg"></picture>
        <imagecitation>"Fake news" by Jorge Franganillo/flickr, CC BY 2.0</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>
  
  <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Cognitive Anthropology: Attraction and Misinformation—The Study</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
        <para>The premise of Acerbi’s (2019) study was that the rapid spread and general cultural acceptance of certain types of online misinformation is due in part to the content creators’ ability to shape misinformation to appeal to evolved cognitive preferences in ways that make it more attractive and memorable—an advantage not shared by truthful information, which is bound by reality.</para>
        <para>In a review of existing literature on the subject, Acerbi notes that narratives featuring negative content have been shown to be more easily recalled than those with positive content and that information is regarded as more truthful when framed negatively than when it is presented with a positive slant—even when the information conveyed in both cases is exactly the same. Previous researchers have suggested that this bias toward negative framing is an adaptive trait, as awareness and avoidance of danger is more evolutionarily advantageous than awareness and pursuit of advantage.</para>
        </contentdata>
      </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture  alt="A collection of Polaroid-style photographs showing the logos of various social networking platforms, overlaid with a transparent world map." picname="people-3175023.jpg"></picture>
        <imagecitation>"logos" by Geralt/pixabay, CC BY 2.0</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>
  

  <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Cognitive Anthropology: Attraction and Misinformation—The Study</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
        <para>This study looked at the impact of negatively, positively, and neutrally framed online articles and their cultural acceptance as valid and true, even when they were later proven false. In addition to the overall slant of the information, the study examined the content of the articles for the presence of seven specific content categories that are believed to appeal to cognitive preferences and contribute to cultural acceptance: threat-related information; sexually related information; information that elicits disgust; minimally counterintuitive information (MCI), which is information that mostly conforms to human expectations of how the world works but violates those expectations in a small number of ways; information that runs counter to essentialist thinking, a subset of MCI; information related to social interactions, including gossip; and the presence of celebrities. Finally, due to the widespread influence of online misinformation in politics, the study considered whether the articles were political in nature.</para>
         
      </contentdata>
    </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="Television news reporters, camera operators, and onlookers gathered in front of the driveway of a suburban home." picname='5908569_d2a76de14d_o.jpg'></picture>
        <imagecitation>"Reporter" by Jackie/flickr, CC BY 2.0</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>

  

  <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Cognitive Anthropology: Attraction and Misinformation—Method</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
        <para>To conduct this study, Acerbi began with two lists, compiled by the websites Snopes and Buzzfeed, of popular online information sources known for publishing false or misleading information. From these lists, he narrowed down the misinformation sources to 26 websites, from which he took a sample of 10 articles each, or 260 articles total.</para>
         <para>Then Acerbi and four other people independently reviewed the articles and coded them according to whether the information they contained was presented as positive, negative, or neutral and whether or not they were political in nature. They also coded the articles for the seven categories of information previously identified as cognitive preferences: threat-related information, sexually related information, disgust-related information, MCI, anti-essentialist information, social information, and information about celebrities.</para>
      </contentdata>
      </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="A woman with shoulder-length brown hair, wearing a black jacket over a green and black plaid sweater, looking straight ahead and smiling." picname='BuzzfeedUnsolvedLogo.jpg'></picture>
        <imagecitation>"BuzzFeed Unsolved Logo" by BuzzFeed/TubeFilter, Public Domain</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>

  <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Cognitive Anthropology: Attraction and Misinformation—Analysis</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
        <para>Upon tabulating the results of the coding, Acerbi’s (2019) study found that over 49 percent of the articles studied had a negative slant, 42 percent were neutral, and only 9 percent were positive. Of all the articles studied, 86 percent contained information from one of the seven content categories of interest. A majority of 63 percent featured content from only one or two of the categories, while 12 percent featured three categories; 9 percent, four categories; and 1.5 percent, five. These account for all but two of the articles, one of which featured six of the seven categories, while the other featured all seven.</para>
        <para>Of all the articles analyzed, the most common attributes were the presence of social information and information about celebrities. After those categories, threat-related information was most prevalent. The study yielded statistically significant evidence of the use of negative framing and appeal to cognitive preferences to tell a story.</para>
      </contentdata>
      </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="A woman wearing a black sequined dress on a red carpet." picname='5842733904_7e1bb5fa6c_o.jpg'></picture>
        <imagecitation>"Jen Su - Cannes Film Festival 2011 Red Carpet" by Jennifer Su/flickr, CC BY 2.0</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>

  <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Cognitive Anthropology: Attraction and Misinformation—Results</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
        <para>This study set out to understand the incidence of negative positioning and cognitive preferences in online misinformation. It found that the least truthful articles relied more heavily on negative content, which supports previous research. Of all the articles, 40 percent were coded as political, which accounted for the majority of the celebrity information (the “celebrities” here being politicians). In nonpolitical articles, the most common category after social information was threats; sexual and disgust-provoking content mostly appeared alongside threats and rarely occurred in isolation.</para>
        <para>The results of this study suggest that the cultural success of online misinformation is due in part to its appeal to general cognitive preferences. Specifically, there is statistical relevance to the use of negatively positioned text to spread misinformation, with threat-related information being a prominent factor. There were also positive correlations of misinformation with sexual details and those eliciting disgust.</para>
      </contentdata>
      </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="A crowd of people gathered for a joint session of the U.S. Congress." picname="President_Ronald.jpg"></picture>
        <imagecitation>"President Ronald Reagan Addressing The Joint Session of Congress" by Reagan White House Photographs/White House Photographic Collection, Public Domain</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>
  
 <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Cognitive Anthropology: Attraction and Misinformation—Discussion</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
        <para>Acerbi found a significant difference in the cognitive preferences represented in the political versus nonpolitical articles. Only 19 percent of the political articles contained any preference category other than social or celebrity information, compared to 57 percent of the nonpolitical articles. This suggests that the spread of political misinformation online may be less driven by appeal to negative cognitive preferences than by other factors. Acerbi also suggests that while the efficiency of digital media certainly plays a part in spreading misinformation, this is not the whole story, as the online spread is driven in part by the same cognitive preferences that promote the cultural success of urban legends and other fictional narratives in offline spaces.</para>
         <para>Acerbi's study yielded insight into the habitual modalities and cultural preferences involved in the human capacity to absorb and reproduce information. The study suggests that people’s tendency to seek out articles that appeal to their cognitive preferences provides content creators with a captive audience through which to spread volumes of misinformation.</para>

      </contentdata>
      </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="Four people interacting with their mobile devices." picname='african-american-american-asian-black-casual-caucasian-1457835-pxhere.com.jpg'></picture>
        <imagecitation>"People using smartphones” by Rawpixel, CC0 1.0</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>
<content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Cognitive Anthropology: Attraction and Misinformation—Future Study</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
        <para>Acerbi states that while this study yielded significant findings, more detailed research is required to understand these cultural and anthropological phenomena. Based on this study, he believes that future studies should focus on more specific questions, such as comparing the prevalence of appeals to cognitive preferences in “fake” and genuine news, or perhaps analyzing in greater depth how such appeals contribute to the cultural success of individual articles.</para>
        

      </contentdata>
      </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="Three people sitting and facing a bank of television monitors, one of whom is wearing headphones and working at a control board." picname='48722774092_17d664fde0_o.jpg'></picture>
        <imagecitation>"Television Control Room MSNBC NBC News Newsroom” by Anthony Quintano/flickr, CC BY 2.0</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>

  

  <content>
    <leftcontent> 
      <contenttitle>Cognitive Anthropology: Attraction and Misinformation—Future Study</contenttitle>
      <contentdata>
     
       <para>Further, Acerbi proposes using topic modeling to determine whether a program can be written to automatically detect appeals to cognitive preference and other such attributes, which could support an expanded study of misinformation with a larger or better randomized sample. This kind of study would be a good use of a researcher’s time and resources.</para>
        <para><h3>References/Content Citations, Attributions</h3></para>
          <para>Acerbi, Alberto. 2019. “Cognitive Attraction and Online Misinformation.” <em>Palgrave Communications</em> 5: 15. <a target="_blank" href="https://doi.org/10.1057/s41599-019-0224-y">https://doi.org/10.1057/s41599-019-0224-y</a>.</para>
      </contentdata>
   
      </leftcontent>
    <rightcontent>
        <picture alt="Three people sitting and facing a bank of television monitors, one of whom is wearing headphones and working at a control board." picname='48722774092_17d664fde0_o.jpg'></picture>
        <imagecitation>"Television Control Room MSNBC NBC News Newsroom” by Anthony Quintano/flickr, CC BY 2.0</imagecitation>
    </rightcontent>
  </content>

</dataset>
